# Toast

Toast shows a brief, non-blocking notification to confirm an action or present temporary information. Use it for scenarios where the user needs feedback but not a decision, such as saving, deleting, or changing a status.

For production use, prefer the `useToast()` hook; it handles positioning, stacking, auto-dismiss, and deduplication via `ToastViewport`. The `Toast` component renders the visual toast element inline and is useful for previews, documentation, and static showcases where the viewport lifecycle is not needed.

**Import:** `import {Toast} from '@astryxdesign/core/Toast';`

## Anatomy

| Element | Required | Description |
|---------|----------|-------------|
| Body | Yes | The primary message text describing what happened or what the user should know. |
| End content | No | A trailing action like an Undo button or a link, placed after the body text. |
| Dismiss button | Yes | A close button that lets the user manually dismiss the toast before auto-hide. |

## Best Practices

- **Do:** Keep messages short: only a few words that tell the user what happened, like "Changes saved" or "Message sent".
- **Do:** Add an undo action in the endContent slot for reversible operations like deleting an item, so the user can recover without navigating away.
- **Do:** Use uniqueID to deduplicate toasts that fire from repeated actions, like clicking a save button multiple times.
- **Do:** Use error type for failures that need attention but not immediate action; it persists until dismissed so the user won't miss it.
- **Don't:** Don't use a toast for critical errors that block the user. Use Banner for persistent, in-context messaging that requires acknowledgment.
- **Don't:** Don't put long or multi-line content in a toast; it disappears after 5 seconds and the user may not finish reading.
- **Don't:** Don't show form validation errors as toasts. Use inline field validation so the user can see exactly which field needs fixing.

## Props

| Prop | Type | Default | Description |
|------|------|---------|-------------|
| `body` | `ReactNode` | ??| Primary message content. **(required)** |
| `type` | `'info' | 'error'` | `'info'` | Toast type controlling background color. Error toasts persist until dismissed. |
| `isAutoHide` | `boolean` | ??| Whether the toast auto-dismisses. Defaults to true for info, false for error. |
| `autoHideDuration` | `number` | `5000` | Duration in ms before auto-dismiss. |
| `endContent` | `ReactNode` | ??| Content rendered at the trailing end (e.g. Undo button, link). |
| `uniqueID` | `string` | ??| Unique identifier for deduplication. |
| `collisionBehavior` | `'overwrite' | 'ignore'` | `'overwrite'` | Behavior when a toast with matching uniqueID already exists. |
| `onHide` | `(reason: "auto" | "manual") => void` | ??| Callback fired when the toast is removed. |

## Theming

| Component class | Preferred data attributes | Props | States |
|-----------------|---------------------------|-------|--------|
| `astryx-toast` | `data-type` | type | ??|

Override in defineTheme:
```ts
components: {
  'toast': {
    base: { /* CSS properties */ },
    'type:value': { /* variant-specific */ },
  },
}
```


Related block templates:

  ToastAction
    Persistent toasts with a trailing button or link so the user can act on the notification, like undoing a delete or viewing a report.
  ToastDeduplication
    Prevent duplicate toasts with uniqueID. Use ignore to keep the first toast, or overwrite to replace it with updated content like a progress percentage.
  ToastDismiss
    Show a persistent toast and dismiss it programmatically using the function returned by useToast. Use for long-running operations that need manual cleanup.
  ToastShowcase
    Imperative toast notifications triggered with useToast and rendered in the toast viewport.
  ToastStacking
    Multiple toasts stacking vertically with smooth enter and exit animations. Click repeatedly to see how toasts queue and dismiss.
  ToastTypes
    Info and error toast variants side by side. Info toasts auto-dismiss after 5 seconds, error toasts persist until the user dismisses them.

